Graham Larue

83I-420-7720

graham@glarue.net

()

https://github.com/glarue

https://www.linkedin.com/in/graham-larue-bioioio/

SUMMARY

I am a computational biologist/bioinformatician specializing in comparative genomics and molecular evolution. I am finishing a PhD in Quantitative and Systems Biology from UC Merced (anticipated Spring 2022) with 8+ years of Python experience, and have published first-author bioinformatics research in prominent scientific journals including *Nucleic Acids Research* and *Current Biology*. I also have more than 10 years of experience in the service industry. Going forward, I am interested in building tools for/answering biological questions in the areas of genomics and next-generation sequencing technologies.

EDUCATION

2016 – 2022 **Ph.D. (anticipated)**

Quantitative and Systems Biology University of California Merced

2013 - 2015 M.S.

Cell and Molecular Biology
San Francisco State University

2002 - 2008 B.S.

Biology

University of California Santa Cruz

WORK EXPERIENCE

AUG. 2016 - PRESENT

University of California Merced *Graduate student*

Bioinformatics/molecular evolution doctoral research focused around sequence-based classification and comparative genomics of spliceosomal introns.

JUN. 2019 – SEP. 2019

DOE Joint Genome Institute Summer Graduate Intern

Big data comparative genomic analysis of intron lengths in fungi.

JUL. 2011 – JUL. 2013

University of California Berkeley

Staff Research Associate I - Depts. of Neurobiology & Electrical Engineering

Electrophysiological investigation of mammalian retinal architecture in the labs of Professor Frank Werblin (Nerobiology) and Dr. Long-Sheng Fan (EE).

JAN. 2009 – NOV. 2010

Santa Cruz Biotechnology *Research Assistant*

Microarray screening and sample prep. in hybridoma monoclonal antibody production group.

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES

BASIC R, Julia, Perl, SQL, C++

ADVANCED Python, Bash

TECHNICAL EXPERIENCE

Bioinformatics: Novel machine-learning based intron sequence classification algorithm (intronIC), *de novo* transcriptome assembly, NGS-based eukaryotic gene annotation, custom gene orthology and intron homology identification, BLAST, DIAMOND, HISAT, bowtie, StringTie, STAR, AUGUSTUS, Trinity, PASA, Kallisto, Salmon, samtools, bedtools, fastq-dump

Computing: Linux system administration, GNU coreutils, grep, sed, awk, Slurm

Data visualization: Matplotlib, Seaborn

Wet lab: ELISA, microarray, confocal and two-photon microscopy, multi-electrode array, retinal tissue culture and dissection, patch-clamp, rodent husbandry and euthanasia, sterile technique.

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Larue, G.E., Eliáš, M., Roy, S.W., 2021. "Expansion and transformation of the minor spliceosomal system in the slime mold *Physarum polycephalum.*" *Curr. Biol.* o. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2021.04.050

Moyer, D.C.*, **Larue, G.E.***, Hershberger, C.E., Roy, S.W., Padgett, R.A., 2020. "Comprehensive database and evolutionary dynamics of U12-type introns." *Nucleic Acids Res.* https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkaa464. (*co-first author)

Hudson, A.J., McWatters, D.C., Bowser, B.A., Moore, A.N., Larue, G.E., Roy, S.W., Russell, A.G., 2019. "Patterns of conservation of spliceosomal intron structures and spliceosome divergence in representatives of the diplomonad and parabasalid lineages." *BMC Evol. Biol.* 19, 162. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12862-019-1488-y.

Slabodnick, M.M., Ruby, J.G., Reiff, S.B., Swart, E.C., Gosai, S., Prabakaran, S., Witkowska, E., **Larue, G.E.**, Fisher, S., Freeman, R.M., Gunawardena, J., Chu, W., Stover, N.A., Gregory, B.D., Nowacki, M., Derisi, J., Roy, S.W., Marshall, W.F., Sood, P., 2017. "The Macronuclear Genome of *Stentor coeruleus* Reveals Tiny Introns in a Giant Cell." *Curr. Biol.* 27, 569–575. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2016.12.057.

REFERENCES

References available on request